A Guide to the Papers of the University of Virginia School of Medicine Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1929-1992
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
Papers of the University of Virginia School of Medicine Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, 1929-1992
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library, University of Virginia
MS-50
2 boxes, 5"x10.5"x15.5," 1 foot, 28 folders
Historical Collections
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Dr. Guy M. Harbert, Jr.
Biographical/Historical Information
Dr. Guy Harbert, the donor of this collection, wrote Obstetrics and Gynecology at the University of Virginia 1825 to 1999 (HS-RARE OVERSIZE RG 501 .V5 O37 2001). In his chronology he writes, "For almost 100 years, since its inception in 1825, medical education was listed as the University of Virginia Department of Medicine. In 1827 the appointment of Dr. Robley Dunglison (the first professor of medicine) was expanded to include the title 'Professor of Obstetrics.' Gynecology was first listed as a subject separate from surgery in 1891. Following that date, in general, obstetrics was included in medicine and gynecology in surgery. Dr. Douglas Macon, a 1897 graduate of the Medical School and Charlottesville physician living on High Street, was named Professor of Obstetrics in 1906. He taught obstetrics and was in charge of deliveries. In a reorganization of medical education in 1924, the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology was formed."
Dr. Leroy A. Calkins was recruited to head the new Department. He resigned in 1929 to be replaced by Dr. F. Bayard Carter until the hiring of Dr. Tiffany J. Williams in 1931. Dr. Williams' correspondence, published papers and talks make up a sizeable portion of the collection. Dr. Williams served until his untimely death in 1947. Dr. John M. Nokes who arrived the same year as Dr. Williams as an Assistant Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology became the Acting Chairman. He served in that capacity until 1950 when Dr. W. Norman Thornton, Jr. became Chair. Dr. Thornton was followed by Dr. Paul B. Underwood, Jr. in 1979 who was chair until 1999.
Scope and Content
The collection includes annual reports, budgets, publications by department members, and correspondence which touches on Tiffany J. Williams' hiring, the distribution of patients between Gynecology and Surgery, Martha Jefferson Hospital's response to the opening of Northridge, the prenatal diagnosis program and its relationship to the Department of Pediatrics and the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology, medical students at Norfolk Maternity Center, agreement between the Departments of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Family Practice regarding obstetrical patients, and accommodation of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology and the Radiology Department in regard to ultrasound.
Arrangement
Box one is arranged by date. Box two is arranged by subject.
Contents List
- Correspondence 1929-1939 (Box-folder 001-001)
  The correspondence is all related to Dr. Tiffany J. Williams who was offered the position of Professor of Obstetrics and Gynecology and head of the service at the University of Virginia in a letter from Dean J. C. Flippin. Other correspondence is with Dr. Whitridge Williams of Johns Hopkins Hospital and E. Alderman, President of the University of Virginia and concerns Williams appointment as well as that of John Nokes. Williams wrote Dr. C. S. Lentz, the Superintendent of the UVa Hospital calling to his attention certain deficiencies in the nursing care on the Obstetrical wards at night due to only one nurse being on duty. There is a copy of the "Regulations Governing the Distribution of Gynecological Cases, University Hospital" and letters from Williams to Dr. Flippin and Dr. Harvey Jordan concerning the Department of Surgery and the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology and "the teaching of gynecology and the distribution of the gynecological teaching and ward clinical material."
- Annual reports, correspondence, 1940-1949 (Box-folder 001-002)
- Annual reports, 1950-1954 (Box-folder 001-003)
- Annual reports, 1955-1957 (Box-folder 001-004)
- Annual reports, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 001-005)
- Annual reports, budgets, publication of department members, correspondence, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 001-006)
- Annual reports, budgets, correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box-folder 001-007)
- Annual reports, budgets, publication of department members, correspondence, 1964-1965 (Box-folder 001-008)
- Annual reports, budgets, 1966-1967 (Box-folder 001-009)
- Annual reports, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 001-010)
- Annual reports, budgets, publication of department members, 1970-1971 (Box-folder 001-011)
- Annual reports, budgets, publication of department members, correspondence, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 001-012)
- Annual reports, Staffing Plans for Next Five Years, Equal Opportunity Programs 1974-1975 (Box-folder 001-013)
- Annual reports, Instructional Objectives for a Basic Curriculum in Obstetrics and Gynecology, Notes for New Students, Region I (Virginia) High Risk Maternity Clinic Report, Delivery Statistics, UVa Hospital Annual Statistical Report, Breakdown of High Risk Problems 1976-1978 (Box-folder 001-014)
- Correspondence regarding the Diabetes in Pregnancy Program 1985 (Box-folder 001-015)
- Correspondence regarding the W. Norman Thornton, Jr. Chair, Eminent Scholars Chair in honor of John M. Nokes, Consultant's Reports of Research Program in Reproduction at University of Virginia Medical School, 1988 (Box-folder 001-016)
  Strengths were applauded, but weaknesses were also highlighted in the Consultant's Reports. Those include inadequate space and the need to promote further interaction among reproductive scientists and endocrinology.
- Correspondence regarding Northridge and the Need for the Prenatal Diagnosis & Treatment Center 1989 (Box-folder 001-017)
  Martha Jefferson Hospital Medical Staff finds "profoundly disturbing" the "genesis and implications" of new "oupatient facilities for the practice of pediatrics, internal medicine, and obstetrics and gynecology at Northridge."
- Correspondence regarding the Residency Review Committee for Obstetrics-Gynecology. 1992 (Box-folder 001-018)
  The department status is "Continue Accreditation with Warning." The ACGME notes a number of areas of inadequate compliance.
- Medical genetics correspondence, 1981-1988 (Box-folder 002-001)
  The correspondence includes counseling, laboratory studies, and the cytogenetics laboratory in the prenatal diagnosis program; the cost of amniocentesis and genetic counselors and what percentage of counselor salaries should be paid for by the Department of Pediatrics and what percentage by the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology; and the possibility of a UVa genetics consortium that would promote medical student and graduate teaching, attract funds for collaborative research, make the most of local resources to promote research interests, and learn from each other. Correspondents include Paul Underwood, Robert Blizzard, Thaddeus E. Kelly, W. Allen Hogge.
- Millard B. Savage Fellowship for Residency Training in Obstetrics and Gynecology correspondence, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 002-002)
  Includes a letter from K. R. Crispell.
- Norfolk rotation for medical students correspondence, 1935-1947 (Box-folder 002-003)
  Includes the routine for home deliveries from the Norfolk Maternity Center; Instructions for Students on Outside Obstetrical Service at Norfolk Maternity Center; supervision of medical students in the clinic and home-delivery service; obstetric deaths in Norfolk with more deaths in African-American patients than white; the hiring of an obstetrician at the King's Daughters Clinic; a letter from Williams that it is hoped that better arrangements than home births can be made by May 1948. Correspondents include W.P. Moore, T.J. Williams, G. Bentley Byrd, Elizabeth J. MacKenzie, R. Cornelius Taylor, C.J. Andrews, A. L. Carson, Paige E. Thornhill, and J.C. Sleet.
- Obstetrical patients correspondence, 1980-1983 (Box-folder 002-004)
  The documents concern the agreement between the Departments of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Family Practice regarding obstetrical patients.
- Publications of members of the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology 1928-1963 (Box-folder 002-005)
  Publications are by Tiffany J. Williams, Dorothy D. Brame, F. A. Snidow, William N. thornton, Jr., H. G. Nix, C. H. Mauzy, J.M. Nokes, J.P. Carter, L.A. Wilson, D.J. Brown, T.C. King, M.J. South, L. Graham, L.N. Waters, L.S. Pearce, K.R. Crispell, W. Parson, G.F. Hollifield, E.P. Cawley, J.Q. Hatten, S.A. Kirkpatrick, H.A. Clairborne, H.C. Jones, J.P. Baker, G. Cooper, E.M. Alrich, G.R. Minor, Y-T Hsu, H.B. Mulholland, H.S. McGaughey, E.L. Corey, G.B. Updike, L.M. Talbert, D.G. Hall, W.A. Scoggin, O.G. Bobbitt, C.H. Fox, D.E. Smith, F.G. Turner, W.L. Johnson, C.H. Ficklen, W.L. Johnson, B.W. LaPrade, Joseph L. Yon, and W.P. Anslow. Also included are a paper: "Spontaneous Rupture of Uterus at Six Months Pregnancy" by F. A. Snidow and also Williams' CV, bibliography, and society memberships.
- Residency training information and Minutes of the executive committee meeting of the University of Virginia Hospital 1949--1952 (Box-folder 002-006)
  Meeting minutes are from 1949 and 1950. The June 14, 1949 minutes include notes about pre-natal care of patients and an agreement with the Joint-Health Department. The November 8, 1950 minutes agree to Dr. Thornton's request that the Department of Obstetrics and Gynecology appoint a Straight Obstetrical Interne. Other documents recommend increasing the residency training program in Ob-Gyn from three to four years, and the summary of minutes on a Conference on Relationship between voluntary Health Insurance and Medical Education.
- Ultrasound correspondence, 1978-1989 (Box-folder 002-007)
  Includes accommodation of Departments of Obstetrics and Gynecology and Radiology in regard to ultrasound.
- Williams, Tiffany J., papers and talks 1927-1938 (Box-folder 002-008)
  "Menorrhagia with Low B.M.R. Readings"; "Considerations in Sterility; A Case of Hydatidiform Mole Treated by Vaginal Hysterotomy"; "Mono-Amniotic Twins with Twisted Cords" [by Tiffany J. Williams]; "Classifications and Etiological Considerations of the Toxemias of Pregnancy" by Tiffany J. Williams ( 1930); "Factors in Maternal Mortality" by T.J. Williams (1931); "Prenatal Care - The Need and Methods" by T.J. Williams (1931), "Prenatal Care - The Need and Methods" - Discussion of paper of Dr. T.J. Williams by Beaman Story, another discussion of paper by C.J. Andrews, another discussion of paper by Joseph Bear; "The Causes and Treatment of Uterine Hemorrhage" by T.J. Williams (1933); "Factors in Maternal Mortality" by T.J. Williams (1935); "The Treatment of the Toxemias of Pregnancy" by T.J. Williams (1935); "Treatment of Toxemias of Pregnancy"; "Prenatal Care" by T.J. Williams (1937).
- Williams, Tiffany J., reprints 1933-1938 (Box-folder 002-009)
  Reprints by T.J. Williams from the Virginia Medical Monthly: "Factors in Maternal Mortality," "The Causes and Treatment of Uterine Hemorrhage," "The Treatment of the Toxemias of Pregnancy," and "Prenatal Care."
- Williams Lecture and portrait 1948-1961 (Box-folder 002-010)
  Following the death of Tiffany Williams on August 19, 1947, Eugene S. Groseclose, C.H. Mauzy, W.N. Thornton, and Jack Kight decided that an annual lecture at UVa, to be known as "The Tiffany J. Williams Memorial Lecture" and given by a prominent obstetrician, would be a fitting tribute. It appears from the correspondence that two lectures were indeed held but by 1955 there had been a failure to continue the lectures each spring as originally planned. In 1961 a portrait was painted of Dr. Williams with money from the Williams fund and it appears that was the amount in the fund.